Hi there. In this video,
we'll discuss data
visualization and
how it helps inform
decisions for your project.
Data visualization is the
graphical representation
of information to
facilitate understanding.
That can include graphs,
maps, and tables, to name a few.
Project managers use these
visual representations
for a few reasons.
They're useful for
communicating data
to others because
they help filter
information by
focusing the audience
on the most important
data points and insights.
Visualizations are also
a more efficient way
to summarize information
because they condense
long ideas and facts into
a single image or
representation, and crucially,
they help the viewer
make sense of and
remember the information
being presented.
Visualizations help
aid information
processing and enhance memory.
It plays an active role in
the storytelling process by
helping communicate project
insights to your audience.
Let's go into some familiar types
of data visualizations that
project managers use throughout
the entire life cycle
of the project.
First, let's discuss a common
data visualization tool
used when running the
project: a dashboard.
A dashboard is a type
of user interface,
typically a graph or
summary chart, that provides
a snapshot view of
your project's progress
or performance.
It acts as a centralized
location for
project stakeholders to
draw quick insights.
It can display a tight
summary of metrics,
stats, and key performance
indicators, or KPIs.
A KPI is a measurable
value or metric that
demonstrates how
effective an organization
is at achieving key objectives.
They serve as a great aid
in helping your team and
stakeholders understand if
you're on the right track.
In other words, they
signal if you're
making progress to reach
your success criteria.
In your dashboard, you
may have a summary of
your top KPIs or metrics
and your progress to date.
For instance, if one of
your objectives is for
your project to reach
a 95% customer
satisfaction score
at the end of a
three-month period,
you may track that goal via
thousands of customer
satisfaction surveys.
Rather than displaying a
spreadsheet of each response,
a dashboard is a good place to
summarize those
results and showcase
the average customer
satisfaction score
to see how you are
pacing to your goal.
Similarly, you could also include
other key KPIs that
signify progress,
like a countdown that shows
the number of days until
project launch or the percentage
of the number of issues resolved.
Many project dashboards may
also summarize project
plans, documents,
and reports in one place
and provide a visual of the
status of each of them.
For example, if your
project plan has
hundreds of tasks with varying
degrees of completion,
your dashboard may
summarize the amount of
tasks or milestones completed
at that point in time
and the percentage
of tasks that are in
progress, complete, or not started.
As you may start to notice,
dashboards are great
visualizations for
efficient status updates because
they enable you to group,
summarize, and highlight
top project data points.
Another visualization
that does this is
one that we mentioned
earlier: a burndown chart.
A burndown chart is a
line chart that measures
the time against
the amount of work
done and the amount
of work remaining.
The outstanding
work is usually on
the vertical axis, with the
time visualized horizontally.
This serves as a strong
visualization to help
the team picture the amount
of tasks left to complete.
Similar to line charts,
column charts are
another popular graph
used to signal project
performance and progress.
Column charts are
useful for comparing
different activities or
comparing progress over time.
For instance, you can
show different outputs,
like the number of customers
and the number of
plants delivered,
year-over-year, to demonstrate
growth in change.
Pie charts are useful when
showing the composition of
something or the parts-to-whole
relationship.
All of these simple charts
offer visualizations that
enable you to draw quick
insights and help tell stories.
There are many more in
the following reading that I
recommend checking
out and practicing.
Before that, there is
a final visual tool that
I want you to know about,
which is an infographic.
Infographics are visual
representations of
information, such
as data or facts,
and are typically in the form
of what we call at Google
a "one-pager" or a "one-sheeter."
The difference is that they're
typically concise
summaries of that data.
This is often done
primarily through
graphics or drawings,
emphasizing the
biggest points with
added text for
further explanation.
Use infographics to present
complex information
quickly, professionally,
and clearly, especially
when you may
not be present to share
all the details yourself.
Infographics should be
able to communicate
strong information
without the need for
extra support and explanation.
These are just a few examples of
data visualization in
project management.
Remember, you'll want
to use visuals to
demonstrate and
illustrate situations
like changes over time,
frequency, relationship
correlations,
and to analyze value and risks.
Another important tip
is to make sure that
these visualizations
are accessible.
As we mentioned before,
you'll want to ensure
that your data story
is understood by everyone.
Check out the resources tab
on some of the best practices for
accessible visualizations and
communications. Nice job!
Now that you're
noticing how to use
data to effectively
tell your story,
we'll continue on to the
final piece of this lesson:
learning about
presentation techniques
to present your data.
Meet you in the next video.